A Guide to the Jimmie W. Monteith, Jr. Collection, 1933-1997
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Jimmie W. Monteith, Jr. Collection, 1933-1997
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms1990-062
1 box; 1 cu. ft.
Jimmie W. Monteith, Jr. (1919-1944) was a Lieutenant in the army during World War II. He served his country bravely and was killed on the beaches of Normandy during the D-Day invasion of 1944. He was posthumously awarded the Congressional Medal of Honor. Collection consists primarily of his letters home during World War II. Also includes letters of condolence sent to the family following his death, congratulatory letters for being awarded the Medal of Honor, newspaper clippings, and photographs. Collection also contains the correspondence of his brother, Robert P. Monteith, letters of sympathy following the death of his brother and his father, Jimmie Sr., as well as other letters to and from some of his family members. In addition, there are the letters and notes of John Coulter, who wrote a biography about Monteith.
David B. Robinson and John Coulter
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The Jimmie W. Monteith, Jr. Collection was donated to Special Collections in 1990. Additional materials were donated and added to the collection in 2000.
Biographical Information
Jimmie W. Monteith Jr. was born in Lowmoor, VA in 1919 and raised in Richmond, VA. Monteith attended Virginia Tech from 1937 through 1939 as a student in mechanical engineering. On 4 October 1941, Monteith entered the army and, after basic training, attended one of the first officer training programs at Fort Benning. Assigned to the First Infantry Division and after serving in North Africa and the Sicily campaign, Jimmie Monteith and the 16th Infantry Regiment hit Omaha Beach on D-day at Normandy, France. In charge of 51 men, Monteith guided his troops through the barbed wire and mines that littered the beach under heavy fire from the Germans. After getting his men into position, Monteith went back down the beach and lead two tanks through the mine field and directed them to take out two German machine gun nests. After continuing the assault, Monteith was caught in the crossfire and killed. Less than a year later, his mother accepted the Congressional Medal of Honor for his bravery. A reserve training center in Richmond, VA and an amphitheater in Alabama were both named in his honor. Virginia Tech named a dormitory building after him.
Scope and Content
The Jimmie W. Monteith, Jr. Collection consists of the letters Monteith wrote home while enlisted in the army, as well as cards and correspondence from those wishing to express their sympathy over his death. Also contained in the collection are the letters of his brother, Robert P. Monteith who served in the Pacific during World War II. The collection also includes many other letters and cards, including sympathy cards sent concerning the death of both Robert P. Monteith and Jimmie Monteith, Sr., letters sent to Nancy Monteith from R. Pierce Lumpkin and the typescript of letters from H.P. Straker, the son of Monteith's cousin, Clara Straker. An important part of this collection is the notes of John Coulter, a former Virginia Tech student who researched Jimmie Monteith's life and write a short biography about him.
Arrangement
The collection is separated into five different series, each arranged chronologically.
Series I, Correspondence of Jimmie W. Monteith Jr., contains letters written by Jimmie W. Monteith, Jr., while at war.
Series II, Correspondence and Letters following Death of Jimmie W. Monteith Jr., contains letters of condolences, sympathy cards and information about awards and honors sent following Jimmie W. Monteith Jr.'s death in 1944.
Series III, Correspondence of Robert P. Monteith, contains letters to and from Jimmie's brother Robert P. Monteith as well as the letters of condolences sent following his death in 1954.
Series IV, Family Correspondence, contains correspondence of Monteith family members.
Series V, Collected Information about Jimmie W. Monteith, Jr. and Family, contains newspaper clippings about Jimmie Monteith, Jr., family members, and friends. It also includes the correspondence and notes of John Coulter, the author of a biography about Jimmie W. Monteith Jr.
Contents List
- Correspondence of Jimmie W. Monteith Jr. 1941-1944
  - Correspondence from J.W. Monteith, Jr.
    - 4 Oct 1941 - 28 Dec 1941 (Box-folder 1:1)
    - 16 Jan 1942 - 27 Apr 1942 (Box-folder 1:2)
    - 15 May 1942 - 29 July 1942 (Box-folder 1:3)
    - 13 Aug 1942 - 30 Sept 1942 (Box-folder 1:4)
    - 7 Oct 1942 - 27 Dec 1942 (Box-folder 1:5)
    - 1 Jan 1943 - 27 Dec 1943 (Box-folder 1:6)
    - 1 Jan 1944 - 21 May 1944 (Box-folder 1:7)
    - no date (Box-folder 1:8)
    - V-Mail, 1 May 1943 - 31 May 1944 (Box-folder 1:9)
- Correspondence and letters following death of J.W. Monteith, Jr., 1944-1962
  - Letters regarding honors and awards, 10 July 1944 - 25 Sept 1962 (Box-folder 1:10)
  - Correspondence concerning death of J.W. Monteith, Jr., 6 July 1944 - 26 July 1944 (Box-folder 1:11-14)
  - Correspondence concerning death of J.W. Monteith, Jr., 2 Aug 1944 - 4 July 1945 (Box-folder 1:15)
  - Sympathy cards sent to Mrs. Jimmie W. Monteith, Sr., 6 July 1944 - 3 Aug 1944 (Box-folder 1:16)
  - Sympathy cards sent to Miss Nancy Monteith, 7 July 1944 - 3 Aug 1944 (Box-folder 1:17)
  - Florist cards from funeral of J.W. Monteith, Jr., no date (Box-folder 1:18)
- Correspondence of Robert P. Monteith, 1935-1954
  - Correspondence from R.P. Monteith
    - 18 Dec 1942 - 27 Apr 1943 (Box-folder 1:19)
    - 12 May 1943 - 14 Dec 1943 (Box-folder 1:20)
    - 16 Jan 1944 - 27 July 1944 (Box-folder 1:21)
    - 1 Aug 1944 - 25 Dec 1944 (Box-folder 1:22)
    - 3 Jan 1945 - 9 Aug 1945 (Box-folder 1:23)
    - Letters to Robert P. Monteith, 8 Nov 1935 - 16 Sept 1943 (Box-folder 1:24)
    - Correspondence concerning death of R.P. Monteith, 21 May 1954 - 24 May 1954 (Box-folder 1:25)
- Family correspondence, 1933-1956
  - Correspondence concerning death of J.W. Monteith, Sr., 2 Aug 1942 - 17 Aug 1942 (Box-folder 1:26)
  - Letters and notes of Mrs. J.W. Monteith, 30 May 1942 - 18 May 1956 (Box-folder 1:27)
  - Letters and notes of Miss Nancy Monteith, 12 Jan 1933 - 13 Feb 1945 (Box-folder 1:28)
  - Correspondence of R. Pierce Lumpkin to Nancy Monteith, 7 Apr 1936 - 23 Aug 1936 (Box-folder 1:29)
  - Typescript of WWII letters of H.P. Straker, 28 July 1940 - 20 Sept 1940 (Box-folder 1:30)
- Collected Information about Jimmie W. Monteith, Jr. and Family
  - Newspaper and Magazine Articles (Box-folder 1:31)
  - Biography of Jimmie W. Monteith, Jr., Fall 1994 (Box-folder 1:32)
  - Citation, Medal of Honor (Box-folder 1:33)
  - Photographs (Box-folder 1:34)
  - Correspondence and Notes of John Coulter (Box-folder 1:35)
  - Information and Maps, D-day Invasion (Box-folder 1:36)